Aslam Aftabuddin

Principal Software Engineer - Scrum Master

Garden Grove, CA - Email me on Indeed: indeed.com/r/Aslam-Aftabuddin/34d5b341962259dd

Solid software engineering background with a track record in building and delivering software solutions. Well seasoned in the agile development environment leading development personnel and meeting stakeholder expectations. Excel in driving cross-functional distributed teams.

- Expert in applying technical solutions to business problems.
- Experienced in Scrum Agile Development (CSM) and leading offshore teams.
- Creative, honest, energetic, responsible, hard working, punctual, organized, creative, detail oriented, team player with excellent problem solving skills.
- Excellent verbal and written communication skills

WORK EXPERIENCE

Principal Software Engineer

Scrum Master - Irvine, CA - January 2015 to Present

Leading and mentoring software development teams and leading engineering initiates.

- Coordinating cross-functional remote distributed Scrum Agile teams and playing role of the Scrum Master including Scrum activities: Grooming, Planning, Sprint Retrospective and Sprint Reviews.
- Involved in other development activities including: assisted in establishing test automation framework, design reviews, code reviews, test case reviews, and release management.
- Aided Product Owners in constructing and grooming User Stories, using tools: JIRA, Confluence and Gliffy.
- Successfully released key major projects including; Document Management System, 3rd, 2nd, 1st Generation public RESTful API, Document Management System, Self User Management portal.
- Played crucial role as SME supporting other departments including IT infrastructure and Application Support.
- Closely worked with software engineers, IT infrastructure personnel and DBA to provide practical software solutions.
- Assisting Product Owners by participated in requirements gathering sessions with stakeholders, identifying ideas and requirements, utilizing tools such as; whiteboarding, Mind-Maps, and diagrams to verify and communicate ideas.
- Instrumental in transforming the legacy applications into an event driven architecture by way of utilizing technologies such as: Microservice architecture, Restful services, and Message Queues.
- Developed multiple software tools to help development including: mock SMTP service and tool for Microservice monitoring.
- Continuously, improved the company's main SaaS solution.
- Technologies and tools used: Spring framework, Spring-Boot, Hibernate, SOA, Microservices, Web services, XML, JSON, HTML, Javascript, Bootstrap, JQuery, AngularJS, MS SQL, Maven, Kapow Software, RabbitMQ, TestNG, Selenium, Windows, Linux, Bamboo, Stash, GIT, Confluence, Gliffy

Recent Projects

Document Management System

- Was instrumental in designing, implementing the company's dynamic document management system for the legal/compliance department.
- This included the following features: document template management, template rule management, workflow and session management, document acknowledgement tracking.

- Utilized Microservices architecture; System encompassed 4 microservices.
- As resources are document based utilized MongoDB as datasource.
- Worked with remote distributed teams.

3rd Generation RESTful API

- Was instrumental in designing, implementing and leading a team of 5 engineers to establish the company's 3rd Generation API based on JSON objects.
- The API had the following features: API security (Authentication and Authorization), Order Placement, Order Retrieval, Report Retrieval, API Audit for Troubleshooting, Webhooks, Multi-Tenant support.
- Utilized Microservices architecture; System encompassed 11 microservices.
- Established event driven solution with asynchronous communication using RabbitMQ to communicate with backend systems.
- As resources are document based utilized MongoDB as datasource.
- Established automation testing using REST-Assured to aid in the Continuous Integration (CI) process.

Status Change Publisher (Foundation for Event Driven System)

- Designed and implemented first ever attempt to make legacy systems event-driven.
- As many distributed legacy systems where accessing and modifying orders, it was challenging to identify and upgrade each access point. Therefore, implemented system using database triggers to notify a data change and ultimately publish the event to RabbitMQ.
- Worked in close collaboration with DBA's to validate solution.
- This system is now being depended upon by many other systems benefiting from the published events.

Senior Software Developer

Scrum Master - Irvine, CA - August 2010 to December 2014

Played a key role in guiding scrum team as the Scrum Master and providing software solutions.

- Coached and trained offshore new scrum teams with Scrum Agile process and company's software systems, and business model.
- Established multiple client and vendor based B2B integrations by way of establishing an integration framework for order fulfillment and result delivery.
- Played a key role in building Self User Management system using LDAP for user account and credentials management that communicated with legacy systems to enhance customer user experience.
- Worked on multiple projects spanning various areas of systems to upgrade and introduce new features to software: including client web portal, administration web portal, reporting systems, system performance enhancements, and system infrastructure upgrades.
- Designed multiple software tools to help engineers in development and QA personnel in testing including: webservice communication tool, client and vendor integration testing tool.
- Worked closely with stakeholders, product owners, project managers, and product managers in identifying requirements and expectations and utilized tools such as; whiteboarding, Mind-Maps, and diagrams to verify and communicate ideas.
- Responsible for release management
- Technologies and tools used: Spring framework, Hibernate, SOA, Web services, XML, JSON, HTML, Javascript, Bootstrap, JQuery, Maven, MS SQL, Windows, Linux, Bamboo, Stash, GIT, Confluence, Gliffy.

Software Engineer

Scrum Master - Lake Forest, CA - November 2006 to August 2010

Involved in requirements gathering sessions with key stakeholders.

- Instrumental in designing and building core software modules.
- Designed User Interfaces for many sub-systems.

- Developed B2B system integration with 3rd party systems.
- Technology Used: Spring framework, web services, Hibernate, Jakarta Ant, Adobe Flex.

Software Developer

AccurateSource.Com Inc - Fullerton, CA - August 2002 to November 2006

Fullerton, CA)

- Designed and implemented company's client facing e-commerce web applications.
- Established internal administrative web portals to process orders.
- Interacted between managers and operational staff to develop user-friendly and functional system.
- Implemented Visual Basic application for operational task automation.
- Designed database in Sybase, Integrated e-commerce services, data storage and retrieval systems.
- Responsible for release management
- Technology Used: JSP, Java, Sybase, XML, CSS, JavaScript, Visual Basic 6.

Design Engineer (Part-time)

AccurateSource.Com Inc - San Jose, CA - August 2005 to January 2006

Implemented a native I2C interface to Epson S1D12000 Series LCD Controller on a I2C bus.

- Included understanding the operation of I2C bus and the Epson controller, and some Phillips controllers.
- Designed a PCB for the system using Eagle Layout Editor.
- Prepared detailed parts list of all components.
- Utilized Verilog as an HDL, and used ACTEL's ProASIC Plus FPGA to simulate design.

Application Programmer

Native Names Corporation - Santa Monica, CA - March 2001 to July 2002

Member of a team that developed multilingual Internet services.

- Created various entry forms, and web page designs for multilingual email.
- Provided validation code for forms and virtual multilingual keypad using JavaScript.

EDUCATION

Bachelor of Science in Computer Engineering

California State University Fullerton May 2009

California State University Northridge May 2004

ADDITIONAL INFORMATION

SKILLS

- Technologies: Microservices architecture, MVC, SAO, Web services, XML, XSLT, XPATH, Java, Spring Framework, Spring-Boot, Hibernate, RabbitMQ, REST-Assured, TestNG, Selenium
- Database: MongoDB, MS SQL Server, MySQL
- Web Technologies: HTML, Javascript, AngularJS, CSS
- Repositories & Tools: Atlassian Stash, GIT, MS Visual Source Safe
- Build Tools: Atlassian Bamboo, Maven, Ant
- Agile Tools: JIRA, Atlassian Confluence, Gliffy
- Operating System: Linux & Windows

Excellent communication skills, ability to work closely with Product Owner, stakeholders and IT infrastructure eam.					
					